Diagnosis relies on a tiered approach.
Endomyocardial biopsy remains the histological gold standard
— Dallas criteria require lymphocytic infiltration and
myocyte necrosis — though sensitivity is limited
by sampling error.
Cardiac MRI with Lake Louise Criteria is
now the preferred non-invasive modality: T2-weighted imaging
identifies myocardial edema; T1 mapping and extracellular
volume fraction quantify inflammation; and late gadolinium
enhancement in a non-ischemic distribution confirms myocardial
injury.
Biomarkers including troponin I or T, CRP,
and BNP support diagnosis and risk stratification.
ESC guidelines recommend CMR in all patients
with suspected myocarditis when echocardiography is inconclusive.