Diagnosis relies on troponin elevation, ECG
changes including ST segment abnormalities, elevated
B-type natriuretic peptide, and cardiac imaging.
Echocardiography demonstrates left ventricular dysfunction.
Cardiac MRI shows myocardial inflammation and
scar distribution.
Management is primarily supportive with guideline-directed
medical therapy for heart failure.
Severe, fulminant cases may require mechanical
circulatory support or transplantation.
Long-term follow-up with serial imaging and
risk stratification is essential given the
potential for progression to cardiomyopathy.