Acute myocarditis presents with severe hemodynamic
complications.
Acute heart failure develops from acute
ventricular dysfunction and is often refractory
to standard therapy.
Fulminant myocarditis may require mechanical circulatory
support.
Malignant arrhythmias including ventricular tachycardia and
ventricular fibrillation account for sudden cardiac
death risk.
High-degree atrioventricular block may necessitate temporary
pacing.
Cardiogenic shock—the most severe presentation—is characterized
by hypotension, tissue hypoperfusion, and elevated
lactate, requiring intensive care and mechanical
support.