Management is stratified by disease severity.
For hemodynamically stable patients, standard heart failure
therapy — ACE inhibitors, beta-blockers, and diuretics
— is the cornerstone.
Competitive athletic activity must be restricted for
a minimum of 3 to 6 months,
given the risk of arrhythmic death during
myocardial inflammation.
In fulminant myocarditis with cardiogenic shock, early
mechanical circulatory support — intra-aortic balloon pump,
Impella, or veno-arterial ECMO — is critical
and has been shown to bridge patients
to recovery.
Immunosuppressive therapy with corticosteroids is indicated for
giant cell myocarditis and cardiac sarcoidosis.
IVIG may be considered in viral etiologies
in pediatric patients.
ICD implantation should be deferred until myocardial
recovery is assessed at 3 to 6
months.