The adverse effects of myocarditis are clinically
diverse and potentially fatal.
Acute heart failure occurs in up to
30 percent of hospitalized cases, with a
subset developing fulminant myocarditis — characterized by
rapid hemodynamic collapse and cardiogenic shock —
carrying a short-term mortality exceeding 70 percent
without mechanical circulatory support.
Arrhythmias represent the second major category: ventricular
tachycardia and fibrillation are the primary mechanisms
of sudden cardiac death; complete AV block
may require temporary pacing; and atrial fibrillation
is common in the inflammatory phase.
Thromboembolic events occur secondary to left ventricular
dysfunction and endocardial inflammation.
Chronic dilated cardiomyopathy develops in 10 to
20 percent of patients, with persistent LV
dysfunction at 6 months being the strongest
predictor of adverse long-term outcomes.