Etiologically, myocarditis is broadly classified into
infectious, autoimmune, toxic, and vaccine-associated categories.
Viruses account for the majority of
cases — Coxsackievirus B historically, though
SARS-CoV-2 has emerged as a significant
cause.
Autoimmune etiologies include giant cell myocarditis,
cardiac sarcoidosis, and systemic lupus.
Toxic causes encompass immune checkpoint inhibitors,
anthracyclines, and clozapine.
Vaccine-associated myocarditis — particularly following mRNA
COVID-19 vaccination — is now well-characterized,
predominantly affecting males aged 16 to
29, with a generally favorable short-term
prognosis.